Guide to the Toba Pato Tucker Photographs and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Toba Pato Tucker photographs and papers
1950-2015
1977-2015
WA MSS S-2604
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
202.29
(283 boxes)
Portraits of individuals from other communities and locales include street portraits of pedestrians in New York City; residents of a drug rehabilitation program at facilities throughout New York State; the people of Heber Springs, Arkansas, the rural town photographed decades earlier by Mike Disfarmer; and African American members of the First Baptist Church of Riverhead, New York. Tucker's commission work includes portraits of individuals, couples, and families. Her personal photography projects include portraits of family members, friends, and bodybuilders, as well as seascape and landscape photography. The subjects for Tucker's portraiture have come principally from Native American populations. These include members of the Onondaga Nation, Shinnecock Indian Nation, Navajo Nation, and Montaukett Indians. Tucker has also documented Native American artists from pueblos throughout the southwestern United States. This collection documents the career of Toba Pato Tucker as a portrait photographer, circa 1950-2011, and landscape photography since 2010, with the bulk of the collection from 1977 to 2015. The photographic materials in this collection consist of exhibition prints, work prints, and negatives for nine major projects, as well as her commission work and personal photography. The papers largely support her photographic work and consist of her project files, which include background research, correspondence, and oral history interviews. The papers also include exhibition catalogs, publications, and publicity material produced for projects, as well as a small amount of personal papers.
Tucker, Toba
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, the Thomas W. Streeter Fund, the Hall Park McCullough Fund, and the Walter Jennings Memorial Fund, 2007.
The exhibition and work prints for the Native American Relocation Project were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2008.
The exhibition and work prints for the Shinnecock Indians of Eastern Long Island Portraits were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2010.
The exhibition prints for the Landscapes of the American West were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2011.
The exhibition prints for the Photographs of Africa were a gift of Toba Pato Tucker, 2011.
The exhibition prints for Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest, Portfolios #1, were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2013.
The work prints for Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest, Portfolio #1, were a gift of Toba Pato Tucker, 2013.
The exhibition prints and work prints for Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest, Portfolio #2, were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2015.
The exhibition prints and work prints for Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest, Portfolio #3, were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2017.
The exhibition prints and work prints for Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest, Portfolio #4, were purchased from Toba Pato Tucker on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 192-199, 201-202, 205, 208-210, 212, 216, 218, 234, and 253 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 236: Restricted material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Toba Pato Tucker (born 1935)
Toba Pato Tucker refers to herself as "a contemporary American documentary portrait photographer" who "strives to record continuity and change in American culture for history and artistic purposes with a particular interest in Native American populations."
Born and raised in the Bronx, New York, Toba Pato married Robert Paul Tucker (Yale 1944) in 1956. They, and their daughter, Dena Suzanne Tucker, lived in West Hartford, Connecticut. After the marriage ended, Toba Pato Tucker returned to New York City.
Initially a self-taught amateur photographer, Tucker began her professional career after attending a workshop taught by Harold Feinstein in 1976. In her early work, she used a Pentax camera that exposed thirty-five millimeter film. In 1976, she bought a used Hasselblad camera that exposed 120 millimeter film. The following year her friend and mentor Toby Old helped her master the intricacies of the Hasselblad as well as how to develop black and white film and print fine art silver gelatin photographs. Although Tucker occasionally used other cameras, the Hasselblad was her primary camera for the remainder of her career. Primarily a black and white photographer, Tucker occasionally used color negative film. From 1978 to 1980, she taught at the International Center of Photography in New York City.
Over her career, the subjects for her portraiture have chiefly come from Native American populations. These include members of the Onondaga Nation, Shinnecock Indian Nation, Navajo Nation, and Montaukett Indians. Tucker has also documented Native American artists from pueblos throughout the southwestern United States.
Tucker also created portraits of individuals from other communities and locales, including street portraits of pedestrians in New York City and Minneapolis, Minnesota; residents of Day Top Village, a drug rehabilitation program with facilities throughout New York State; the people of Heber Springs, Arkansas -- the rural town photographed decades earlier by Mike Disfarmer (1884-1959); and African American members of the First Baptist Church of Riverhead, New York. During her work with residents of Day Top Village and Heber Springs, Tucker taped oral history interviews with her portrait subjects.
In 2012, Tucker began concentrating on landscape photography, epitomized by a project to document the American West using the work of nineteenth century photographers as reference points.
In her commission work, Tucker created portraits of individuals, couples, and families. Other projects included portraits of family members, friends, and bodybuilders, as well as seascape and landscape photography.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the photographic career of Toba Pato Tucker, including her various photographic projects. These projects include:
Street Portraits (1977): Portraits of people on the street in New York City and Minneapolis.
Daytop Village Portraits (1977-1980): Portraits of residents of a therapeutic drug rehabilitation program with facilities throughout New York State.
Navajo Portraits (1981): Portraits of Navajo people living in Navajo-Hopi Joint Use Area, also known as Black Mesa or Big Mountain in Navajo County, Arizona, during which project she also made landscape photographs of the Navajo Reservation.
Shinnecock Indians of Eastern Long Island (1984-1987): Portraits of a multi-racial Native American reservation located on the east side of Shinnecock Bay in Southampton, Long Island, New York.
Black History & Folklife Project, Riverhead, New York (1986): Portraits of African American members the First Baptist Church of Riverhead, New York.
Heber Springs Portraits (1989-1991): Portraits of residents of a rural Arkansas town, which consciously revisited the subject matter photographed decades earlier by Mike Disfarmer (1884-1959).
Haudenosaunee, Portraits of the Firekeepers, The Onondaga Nation (1991-1992): Portraits of tribal members on the Onondaga Reservation in upstate New York, as well as landscapes showing community buildings.
Pueblo Artists, Portraits (1995-1997): Photographs of Native American artists and their families from pueblos throughout Arizona and New Mexico.
Native American Relocation Project (2001): Portraits of Native Americans whose families moved to southern California under programs sponsored by the federal government in the 1950s.
Re Viewing the American Landscape, West & Southwest (2012-): Landscape photography of the American West that references the work of nineteenth century photographers.
Additional material in this collection also documents several smaller projects, which include:
The Urban Indian (1980): Portraits from the Native American Center, Los Angeles, California.
Portraits of the Montaukett Indians of eastern Long Island (1986 and 1988).
Portraits of amateur bodybuilders in Southampton, Long Island (1986-1987).
Landscapes of Abiquiu Lake, New Mexico (2003).
Landscapes of the American West (2010-2011).
Photographs of Africa (2011).
The collections also documents personal portraits, landscapes, and seascapes Tucker has made throughout her career as well as commissioned portraits she made between 1980 and 2003.
The photographic materials in the collection consist of exhibition prints, work prints, and negatives for Tucker's various projects, as well as her commissioned work and personal photographs. Her project files include background research, correspondence, and interviews. The collection includes exhibition catalogs, publications, and publicity material produced by projects as well as a small quantity of her personal papers.
Many photographs of Native Americans in the collection document these individuals and their communities during the late twentieth century. Most of the portraits depict Native Americans wearing modern clothes, which underscore their contemporary lives. Portraits of individuals wearing traditional costumes also appear throughout the collection, reflect Tucker's interest in tracing cultural continuity as well as change within Native American communities.
The photographs and papers for the Daytop Village Portraits project provide unique documentation of drug rehabilitation centers during the 1970s. The audio interviews frequently report the circumstances of individuals that led them to drug use and of their eventual entry into the rehabilitation center, while other audio recordings provide glimpses into the program from the residents' vantage point.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Photographs, circa 1970-2003. II. Project Files, circa 1950-2005. III. Personal and Professional Papers, circa 1965-2006. IV. Additions 2008-2011, 1995-2011. V. Re Viewing the American Landscape West & Southwest, 2012-2015.
African Americans -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Portraits; Montauk Indians -- Pictorial works; Navajo Indians -- Pictorial works; Onondaga Indians -- Pictorial works; Portrait photography -- Arkansas -- Heber Springs; Portrait photography -- United States; Pueblo artists -- Pictorial works; Pueblo Indians -- Pictorial works; Shinnecock Indians -- Pictorial works; Heber Springs (Ark.) -- Pictorial works; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Riverhead (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Audiotapes; Negatives (photographs); Oral histories (document genres); Photographic prints; Portraits; Disfarmer, Mike, 1884-1959; Tucker, Toba
- Photographs, circa 1970-2003; Series I; (190 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Exhibition Prints, Work Prints, Negatives and Contact Sheets, and Color Slides.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I mainly consists of photographic materials created by Tucker during her projects, as well as her commissioned portraits and personal portraits. The photographic material documents the evolution of images from negatives captured during portrait sessions through their development into exhibition prints. The negatives show variant images captured by Tucker of subjects, while the related work prints, contact sheets, and negatives frequently include her notes for printing exhibition prints. The exhibition prints relay her final vision for the each image. Most of the photographic prints are black and white, usually with a square frame, although she included color photographic materials in a few projects, including the Navajo Portraits and the Onondaga Nation Portraits. Tucker rarely crops her images and her prints usually show the entire image captured in her negatives.
  - Exhibition Prints, (73 boxes)
    Arranged by the size of the photographic prints under four headings: 8 inches by 10 inches or smaller; 11 inches by 14 inches; 16 inches by 20 inches; 20 inches by 24 inches. Within each size, prints are arranged by projects (Day Top Village Portraits, Navajo Portraits; Shinnecock Indians of Eastern Long Island; Riverhead; Heber Springs Portraits; Onondaga Nation Portraits; Pueblo Artists, Portraits; Urban Indians in Southern Galifornia) followed by Commmission Work, Additional Projects, Personal Portraits, Photographs of Toba Tucker by Other Photographers, Portraits of Toba Tucker by Daytop Village Residents, and Photographs by Others Collected by Toba Tucker. Some categories are represented in all three sizes of photographic prints; others are represented in one or two sizes.
    Within the categories, prints are arranged chronologically by date of creation except for Photographs of Toba Tucker by Other Photographers and Photographs by Others Collected by Toba Tucker which are organized alphabetically by the creator's last name.
    Color work, where it exists, has been listed separately for each project, following the chronological arrangement of black and white prints.
    This subseries consists of exhibition prints that usually became Tucker's final product of a particular image or became the basis for reproductions in her publications.
    The subseries also includes portraits of Tucker created by other photographers, including portraits of her created by residents of the Daytop Village drug rehabilitation center and work by other photographers collected by Tucker.
    A small selection of photographs are present in Series II, Project Files, in the subseries documenting the Heber Springs Portraits, and consist of original photographs and copies of photographs created by Mike Disfarmer, as well as her personal informal photographs related to the project. Examples of publications that reproduced her photographs are present in Series III, Personal and Professional Papers, in the subseries, Publications that Include Images by Tucker.
    Each folder in the 11 inches by 14 inches and 16 by 20 inches subseries contains a single photographic print.
    - 8 inches by 10 inches and smaller
      - Daytop Village Portraits
        - Phil Hefft, 1979 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Reid Barnett, 1980 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Navajo Portraits
        - Kalutah, 1981 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Louise Bahe, 1981 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Selina James, 1981 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Toba Tucker and her Chevrolet Van, 1981 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Elle Benally, 1981 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Bernice Begay and Bah Chee, 1981 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Ruby Gishal and Betty Bedoni, 1981 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Anita Begay, 1981 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Stella Begay, 1981 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Shinnecock Indians of Eastern Long Island Portraits
        - Phillip Brown, Jr., 1984 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Edward Gumbs, 1984 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Wayne Duncan, 1984 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Elizabeth Franklin Goodall, 1987 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Naike Bess, 1987 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Heber Springs Portraits
        - Ellen Seaton Habgood, 1989 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Lecil Bishop, 1990 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Pueblo Artists, Portraits
        - San Ildefonso, New Mexico, 1995 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Lonnie Vigil, 1995 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Bob Hazous, 1995 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Gregory Lomayesva, 1995 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        - Estella Loretto and Fawn Eagle-Day, 1995 November 22 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - Diego Romero, 1995 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - Florence Aguilar Naranjo and Alfred Aguilar, 1995 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Mark Swazo-Hinds, 1995 December 4 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Coral Gutierrez Naranjo, Kathy Gutierrez Naranjo, Geraldine Gutierrez, Rose Gutierrez, and Ann Gutierrez, 1995 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Geraldine Gutierrez and Rose Gutierrez, 1995 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Coral Gutierrez Naranjo and Kathy Gutierrez Naranjo, 1995 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - Lonnie Vigil and Melinda Vigil, 1995 December 11 (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - Juan Tafoya, 1995 December 13 (Box 2, Folder 31)
        - Nelson Tsosie, 1995 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 32)
        - Dolly Naranjo Neikrug, 1995 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - Lu Ann Tafoya and Michelle Browning, 1995 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Puye Cliff Dwellings, Santa Clara Pueblo, New Mexico, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - Felix Vigil, 1996 March 19 (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Margarete Bagshaw-Tindel, 1996 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 37)
        - Pablita Velarde, 1996 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        - Jeff Roller, 1996 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 39)
        - Toni Roller, 1996 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 40)
        - Toni Roller, Susan Roller, Cliff Roller, and Jeff Roller, 1996 April 17 (Box 2, Folder 41)
        - Margaret Tafoya, 1996 April 24 (Box 2, Folder 42)
        - Steven Herrera, 1996 April 25 (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Grace Medicine Flower, 1996 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 44)
        - Joseph Naranjo, 1996 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 45)
        - Mollie Naranjo, 1996 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 46)
        - Robert Naranjo, 1996 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 47)
        - Mateo Romero, 1996 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 48)
        - Hubert Candelario, 1996 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 49)
        - Juanita Suazo-Dubray, 1996 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 50)
        - Ralph Suazo, John Suazo, and Shaw Suazo, 1996 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 51)
        - Cora L. Durand, 1996 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 52)
        - Anthony Durand and Cora L. Durand, 1996 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 53)
        - Anthony Durand, working, 1996 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 54)
        - Rose Naranjo, Dolly Naranjo Neikrug, Jody Naranjo, Jade Chavez, and Coral Chavez, 1996 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 55)
        - Margaret Archuleta, 1996 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 56)
        - Frances Martinez, 1996 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 57)
        - Robert Dale Tsosie, 1996 June 25 (Box 2, Folder 58)
        - Deborah Jojola-Sanchez, 1996 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 59)
        - Charles Sunrise Trujillo, 1996 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 60)
        - Cloud Eagle, 1996 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 61)
        - Carmelita Dunlap, Marchia Appleleaf Fender, and Justine Fender, 1996 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 62)
        - Phillip C. Martinez, 1996 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 63)
        - Phillip C. Martinez, David Martinez, and Benito Martinez, 1996 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 64)
        - David Gaussoin, 1996 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 65)
        - Tazbah Ann Gaussoin, 1996 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 66)
        - Lydia Tsosie and Carl Tsosie, 1996 August 29 (Box 2, Folder 67)
        - Cliff Fragua, 1996 September 19 (Box 2, Folder 68)
        - Elvira Montoya, 1996 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 69)
        - Lena Garcia, Bertie Pasqual, Clara Paquin, and Elvira Montoya, 1996 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 70)
        - Augustine Lovato, 1996 September 24 (Box 2, Folder 71)
        - Bea Duran-Tioux, Bay-Povi Tioux, Nana Tioux, and Summer Tioux, 1996 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 72)
        - Ignacia Duran with her daughters and granddaughters, 1996 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 73)
        - Virgie D. Nutima and Erica Leno, 1996 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 74)
        - Reyes Duran Herrera, Rachel Herrera, Roxanne Herrera, and Raeann Herrera, 1996 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 75)
        - Jean Baca and Starr Tafoya, 1996 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 76)
        - Roxanne Swentzell, 1996 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 77)
        - Norman C. Pacheco, 1996 September 27 (Box 2, Folder 78)
        - Harry Fonseca, 1996 October 4 (Box 3, Folder 79)
        - John F. Gonzales, 1996 November 13 (Box 3, Folder 80)
        - Elizabeth Montoya, Margie Montoya, Michelle Sandoval, and Sarah Sandoval, 1996 November 13 (Box 3, Folder 81)
        - Michael Kanteena, 1996 November 19 (Box 3, Folder 82)
        - Dusty Naranjo and Forrest Naranjo, 1996 November 20 (Box 3, Folder 83)
        - Christine McHorse, 1996 November 20 (Box 3, Folder 84)
        - Cavan Gonzales, 1996 November 22 (Box 3, Folder 85)
        - Calvin Analla, Jr., 1997 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 86)
        - Philopita Torres and Elvis Torres, 1997 January 29 (Box 3, Folder 87)
        - Joe Cajero, Jr., 1997 January 30 (Box 3, Folder 88)
        - Juanita C. Fragua, 1997 January 30 (Box 3, Folder 89)
        - Marie G. Romero, 1997 January 30 (Box 3, Folder 90)
        - Joel C. McHorse, 1997 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 91)
        - Ramoncita C. Sandoval, 1997 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 92)
        - Floyd R. Solomon, 1997 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 93)
        - Verna Solomon, 1997 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 94)
        - Sue Dailey, 1997 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 95)
        - Dora Tse Pe, 1997 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 96)
        - Garrett J. Lorenzo, Sr., 1997 February 24 (Box 3, Folder 97)
        - Michael D. Garcia and Michael A. Dukepoo, 1997 February 26 (Box 3, Folder 98)
        - Jimmy Calabaza, 1997 March 19 (Box 3, Folder 99)
        - Cippy Crazyhorse, 1997 March 20 (Box 3, Folder 100)
        - Geronima C. Shendo, 1997 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 101)
        - Glendora Daubs and B. J. Fragua, 1997 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 102)
        - Josephine M. Sando, 1997 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 103)
        - Marie Lupe Romero, 1997 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 104)
        - Johnnie Arquero, 1997 March 26 (Box 3, Folder 105)
        - Josephine Arquero, 1997 March 26 (Box 3, Folder 106)
        - Mike Bird-Romero, 1997 March 27 (Box 3, Folder 107)
        - Cordi Gomez and Glenn Gomez, 1997 April 4 (Box 3, Folder 108)
        - Gail Bird, 1997 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 109)
        - Yazzie Johnson, 1997 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 110)
        - Charlie Bird, 1997 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 111)
        - Geronima Cruz Montoya, 1997 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 112)
        - Elizabeth Medina, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 113)
        - Esther H. Cajero, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 114)
        - Marcellus Medina and his grandson, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 115)
        - Mary Tenorio, Paulita Pacheco, and Hilda Coriz, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 116)
        - Juana Marchia Pecos, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 117)
        - Robert Tenorio family, 1997 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 118)
        - Dawn Antelope, 1997 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 119)
        - Jonathan Warm Day, 1997 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 120)
        - Tom Ready To Hunt, 1997 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 121)
        - Jonathan Warm Day and Dawn Antelope, 1997 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 122)
        - Connie Gaussoin and Tazbah Ann Gaussoin, 1997 May 23 (Box 3, Folder 123)
        - Wayne Nez Gaussoin, 1997 May 23 (Box 3, Folder 124)
        - George Rivera, 1997 June 3 (Box 3, Folder 125)
        - Quella Romero Musgrave, 1997 June 3 (Box 3, Folder 126)
        - Adam Martinez, 1997 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 127)
        - Adam Martinez and Santana Martinez, 1997 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 128)
        - Marvin Martinez, 1997 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 129)
        - Marvin Martinez and Manual Martinez, 1997 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 130)